<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A sermon preached at Clonmell, on Sunday the sixteenth of September, 1683 at the assizes held for the county palatine of Tipperary / by Jo. Vesey ...</title>
            <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1683</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 37 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 12 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2012-10">2012-10 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A64879</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing V281</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R6797</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">13090796</idno>
            <idno type="OCLC">ocm 13090796</idno>
            <idno type="VID">97361</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A64879)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 97361)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 402:17)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A sermon preached at Clonmell, on Sunday the sixteenth of September, 1683 at the assizes held for the county palatine of Tipperary / by Jo. Vesey ...</title>
                  <author>Vesey, John, 1636-1716.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>22 p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>Printed by Joseph Ray ... for Sam Helsham ...,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>Dublin :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1683.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of original in Huntington Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Psalms CXXII, 6 --  Sermons.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2011-12</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-01</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-03</date>
            <label>Ali Jakobson</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2012-05</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:97361:1"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97361:1" rendition="simple:additions"/>
            <p>A SERMON Preached at CLONMELL, ON <hi>SUNDAY</hi> the Sixteenth of <hi>September,</hi> 1683.</p>
            <p>AT THE ASSIZES Held for the COUNTY PALATINE of TIPPERARY.</p>
            <p>By JO. VESEY Maſter of Arts of <hi>Trinity</hi> College near <hi>Dublin,</hi> and Miniſter of <hi>Abbyleaſe.</hi>
            </p>
            <q>O pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſhall proſper that love thee. <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 122.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </q>
            <p>
               <hi>D<g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>BLIN,</hi> Printed by <hi>Joſeph Ray,</hi> at <hi>College-Green,</hi> for <hi>Sam. Helſham</hi> Bokſeller, at the <hi>College-Arms,</hi> in <hi>Caſtle-ſtreet.</hi> 1683.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="dedication">
            <pb facs="tcp:97361:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:97361:2"/>
            <head>
               <hi>To His GRACE, MICHAEL,</hi> By Divine Providence Lord Archbishop of <hi>ARDMAGH,</hi> Primate and Metropolitan of all <hi>IRELAND,</hi> and Lord High Chancellor of the ſame, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
            </head>
            <opener>
               <salute>May it pleaſe your Grace,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>YOur Grace being ſo eminent a Miniſter of State in this Kingdom, the main Pillar of the <hi>Irish Church,</hi> under the Government, and ſo great an Example of Loyalty and Sted<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dineſs to the Crown, is the reaſon why this Pa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per flies to your Protection, preſuming your Grace will encourage the Principles of Loyalty in others; becauſe they are ſo ſignal in your ſelf.</p>
            <p>It is the joy of all good men to ſee thoſe, who were found faithful in the times of adver<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſity, plentifully rewarded; to ſee thoſe Jewels appendant on the Crown, which formerly had shewed their true value by ſparkling in the dark; and indeed who ſo fit to partake of the bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſings of Peace, which flow from the Fountain of Royal Bounty, as thoſe who in the late times
<pb facs="tcp:97361:3"/> of Apoſtaſie and Confuſion, durſt be Orthodox and Loyal, though it was reputed the worſt of Crimes to be ſo? that which is a juſt Reward to your Grace, is an Encouragement to others to follow your great Example, and the ſame Beams that shine on your Grace, warm and enliven the Seeds of Loyalty in others.</p>
            <p>Honor is not fit for a Malignant, nor does a Garland become the Brow of a Rebel: It is un<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>reaſonable they should expect Favours from His Majeſty, who are diſaffected to the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and with what confidence do they expect to drink of a pure Stream, who caſt Dirt and Mud into the Fountain; as if their grinning at the Higher Powers were a ſufficient reaſon for the King to through Preferments into their Mouths.</p>
            <p>The worſt of your Graces Enemies cannot but acknowledge you to be Orthodox and Loyal: and what can your beſt Friends, or e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven the greateſt Panegyrick ſay more? ſince to be a Chriſtian, and a Subject, to fear God and honour the King, are the two great ends of e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very mans nativity.</p>
            <p>Your Graces experience of the late times will tell you, that a Sermon of this kind preach'd ſome years agoe, would have made the Preach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er
<pb facs="tcp:97361:3"/> to be pull'd down, and given occaſion to an Inſolent Officer to enter the Pulpit with a Back-ſword, and hold forth to the People in Buff. But God be thanked we now may preach Peace and Obedience to our Superiours, with<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>out danger of Banishment, and may exhort Subjects to Loyalty, and Allegiance to their natural Prince, without fear of Impriſonment or Sequeſtration.</p>
            <p>I do not pretend to any thing extraordinary in this Sermon: but the uſefulneſs of Diſcour<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſes of Loyalty at this time, made ſome Perſons of Worth and Sence perſwade me to publish it. I ſubmit my ſelf to your Graces cenſure, and however mean the Piece be, I hope your Judgment will be favourable, becauſe of the honeſty of its deſign. We find that the Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>then Votaries offered to their Tutelar Gods, not only Irrational Creatures, as Birds and Beaſts, but ſometimes even thoſe that were moſt ridiculous and deſpicable; and as we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not imagine any Rational Heathen to be ſo ſot<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tish, as to perſwade himſelf that ſuch Sacrifices were pleaſing to the Gods for their intrinſick value (unleſs he believ'd the Deities to be as ſtupid and ſenceleſs as the Brutes that were of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fer'd to them) but becauſe they were demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrations
<pb facs="tcp:97361:4"/> of the inward affections of the mind: ſo this I hope, though unworthy of ſo great a Patron, may find acceptance, for this reaſon only, becauſe it is an argument of a profound acknowledgment of that Service &amp; Duty which is due to your Grace, not only from me, but from all the Sons of the Church of <hi>Ireland.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>I humbly beg your Graces pardon, for de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>taining you from a better employment of thoſe few Minutes which free you from the weighty Affairs of Church and State. It would be an argument both of want of ſence and good man<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ners in me, to trouble your Grace with a te<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dious Dedication of ſo inconſiderable a work, which yet humbly hopes to be accepted, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe I have no other way of shewing my ſelf to be,</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>May it pleaſe Your Grace, Your Graces moſt Obedient, and moſt devoted humble Servant,</hi> JO: VESEY.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb n="7" facs="tcp:97361:4"/>
            <head>
               <hi>A SERMON preached at</hi> Clonmell, <hi>on</hi> Sunday Septemb. 16. 1683.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>O pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> they ſhall proſper that love thee.</q>
               <bibl>
                  <hi>Pſal. 122.6.</hi>
               </bibl>
            </epigraph>
            <p>WIthout troubling you with any manner of Preface, I will fall immediately upon the Words of my Text, in which there are theſe three things to be taken notice of; Firſt, here is a Duty earneſtly enjoyned. Secondly, there is the thing to be prayed for, and that is <hi>the Peace of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem. Thirdly, there is an Encouragement to this Duty; <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee. O pray for the Peace of</hi> Jeru<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſalem, <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. There is a Duty earneſtly enjoyned, <hi>O pray for the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> That Prayer is a neceſſary Duty incumbent upon all Chriſtians, the Commands of God in my Text, and in ſeveral other places of Scripture, may ſuffici<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ently teſtifie: yet becauſe we are generally ſo diſingenuous, as not to think our ſelves oblig'd by the bare Commands of God, unleſs we reap ſome Benefit by obeying ſuch Com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mands; I will lay down two Reaſons, in order to recom<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mend the Neceſſity of this Duty; and they are, <list>
                  <item>1. Our own Wants and Neceſſities.</item>
                  <item>2. The Goodneſs and Mercy of God, in that he is willing to anſwer our Petitions.</item>
               </list>
            </p>
            <p n="1">1. The firſt Argument to preſs this Duty to our Practice, is our own Wants and Neceſſities. It is one, and not the leaſt, of thoſe Miſeries that attend the whole Race of <hi>Adam,</hi>
               <pb n="8" facs="tcp:97361:5"/> ſtill to want ſomething whilſt we are on this ſide Heaven: The poor man wants Food, the rich man wants Stomach, Health and Digeſtion? ſome men would be liberal, but they have not wherewithal, others are full of Wealth, yet have not a Heart to make uſe of what they poſſeſs; ſome have all things, yet enjoy nothing, for want of being contented with their Condition; the greateſt part of Mankind either wants Grace, or is in danger of falling from it; or if ſome do perſevere unto the end, yet they are not in this world what they ſhall be; they want the bleſſed Viſion of God, which is not to be had till after Death: the beſt of us tranſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>greſs every day, and therefore muſt needs want the Pardon of our Sins for each day. The Wants of the prodigal Son were occaſion'd by his own Riot and Exceſs, and the Diſobe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dience of <hi>Adam</hi> is the cauſe of all our Wants and Neceſſities; and although this be a ſore Evil, and a heavy Diſeaſe; yet he that lay'd on this Curſe, and inflicted this Diſeaſe, has not left us without Remedy. The Curſe is indeed heavy, but the Remedy is light and eaſie: the Diſeaſe is grievous, but the Medicine to cure it is pleaſant, eaſie to be had, and heals infallibly, the pooreſt man may purchaſe it. There is not any of <hi>Adam</hi>'s Poſterity but always ſtands in need of ſome<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>thing or other; the greateſt Wants may be ſupplied by Prayer, and there is no man but may pray, if he pleaſe; and the Duty of Prayer is ſo neceſſary, that without it, we ſhall not only want in this world, but we ſhall be miſerably in want to all eternity; without it we cannot have Remiſſion of our Sins, nor the Gift of Gods Grace beſtow'd upon us; we can<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>not expect to be fed by his Mercy, if we think it too much trouble to implore it; we muſt have a very low eſteem of Gods Bleſſings, if we think them not worth the asking for; and we are very little ſenſible of our Neceſſities, if we will not ſo much as pray to have them remov'd; he is doubly guilty that commits a Fault, and perſiſts in it, and will not ſo
<pb n="9" facs="tcp:97361:5"/> much as ask Pardon for it. In ſhort, whilſt we are on this ſide Heaven, we are continually wanting, there is none that can ſupply our Neceſſities, but God, and there is no other way for us to be ſupply'd, but by petitioning the Throne of Grace: and therefore Prayer muſt needs be a neceſſary Duty. This is the firſt Reaſon, drawn from our own Wants and Neceſſities.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond Reaſon to enforce the Duty of Prayer, is the Mercy of God, in that he is willing to hear us. There is nothing in the world ſo powerful as a man in Prayer, and therefore 'tis call'd the Key of Heaven. What is there ſo difficult, that Prayer cannot attain to? It gives Victory to the weak, and overthrows the Armies of the mighty: it can make the Sun ſtand ſtill for the ſpace of a day: it can bring a Drowth upon the Earth for three years &amp; ſix months, and afterwards cauſe the Rain to fall plentifully upon the ſame: if we are Enemies to God, it can reconcile us to his Favour: if we are in a ſtate of Sin and Death, it can renew the Image of God in us, and put us in a ſtate of Grace: it can purchaſe for us the Bleſſings of this Life (or, which is far better, the Art of Contentment without them) and the Bleſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſigns of the Life to come: by Prayer we are not only in a condition of profiting our ſelves, but of doing good to our Neighbour: by it every man is a Prieſt, and every man may be a <hi>Moſes,</hi> to atone for the Sins of the people; to prevent the Deſtruction of a Nation, though it hang over us; and to bring down publick Bleſſings from on high; the Bleſſings of Peace and Plenty, the Liberty of our Religion, and the Enjoyment of our Eſtates: there is nothing ſo good, but Prayer can purchaſe for us: there is nothing ſo hurtful, but Prayer can avert: nay, though the Sword be in Gods Hand, and his Arm ſtretched forth to ſtrike, and the Judgment be ready to fall upon our heads, yet Prayer is able to appeaſe his Wrath, and withdraw the Arm of the Almighty from
<pb n="10" facs="tcp:97361:6"/> confounding us, and yet all this is not to be imputed to the meer force of Prayer it ſelf, but to the Goodneſs and Mercy of God, who is ſo much in love with this Duty, that he can deny us nothing we ask for faithfully, he will certainly give us the very thing it ſelf, or ſomething as good, or better, if the other be not convenient for us.</p>
            <p>It has been objected by ſome, as an Argument againſt Prayer, That it either ſuppoſeth firſt God to be ignorant of our Prayers; for if not (ſay they) what need we tell God that which he knows already? Or ſecondly, that he is not ſo bountiful to us as he ought, in that he knows our Neceſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſities, and will not help us without ſo much intreaty. Or thirdly, that he is overcome by our Importunities, and Solli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>citations, which is an argument of his Weakneſs, and ſo would argue an Imperfection in him, this was urg'd by one that was once an Atheiſt, but afterwards died a great Penitent. But to this the Anſwer is obvious. For, firſt, Can there be a greater argument of Gods Goodneſs to us, than to give us not only the Bleſſings of this Life, but even Heaven it ſelf for asking? Secondly, We do not pray to inform God of our Neceſſities (that is too groſs a Suppoſition)<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> but to ſhew our Faith, and acknowledge his All ſufficiency, and our Dependance upon him. Thirdly, We are not ſo conceited of our Prayers, as if we thought the meet Force of them, or the Repetition of ſuch and ſuch Words, though they come from a devout Heart, to be able to wreſt a Bleſſing from God, whether he will or no; but that God has ordain'd Prayer as the means and method of making our Addreſſes to his Divine Majeſty. 'Tis true, we are ſaid to wreſtle with God, to prevail upon him, to take Heaven by violence, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> but theſe are figurative Expreſſions, and bold Metaphors, which are no arguments of his Weakneſs, but of his Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs, in that he has given us ſo eaſie a method of addreſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing our ſelves, to him; not is it ſo much the force of our
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:97361:6"/> Prayers themſelves, as his infinite Goodneſs, which moves him to anſwer our Petitions. Ask and ye ſhall receive, is a Promiſe that God will hear our Prayers, and the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God prompted him to make this Promiſe; as an en<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>couragement to perſwade us to this Duty; our Prayers are offered up ſince this Promiſe: and therefore it is not ſo much their Force that works upon God, as his own Good<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs that made him promiſe; it is not any Power in us, but Compaſſion in him. A Petition may be very well drawn up; but if the Prince, to whom it is preſented, be not of himſelf inclin'd to do good, he will never anſwer it meer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly becauſe it is well penn'd. How many do we ſee attend<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing with patience from day to day on the Perſons of great Men for a Favour, and value not the Slights that are put upon them, ſo their Requeſts be at laſt but granted; but God is more merciful: he is more ready to hear than we to pray, and does not only give us what we pray for; but does encourage us even to pray. And therefore, if our own Wants and Neceſſities cannot awake us, let the Goodneſs of God perſwade us to this Duty, who is ſo ready to hear us. This is the ſecond Reaſon to enforce the Duty of Prayer. And ſo I have done with the firſt thing con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſidered in my Text; the earneſt Injunction of a Duty, <hi>O pray.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="2">2. The ſecond thing to be taken notice of, is, the thing we are to pray for, and that is <hi>the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem. This Exhortation is directed to thoſe that think Prayer a Duty, and uſually pray for themſelves; for they that are ſo ſtupid, as not to pray for themſelves, will never be per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſwaded to pray for other: and he that neglects his own Advantage, will never be much concern'd for the publick Good. There is nothing in the world more plain, than that the publick Peace and Safety of a Nation redounds to the particular Advantage of every perſon in it: and therefore,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:97361:7"/> if men are not ſo publick ſpirited, as to be concern'd for the general Good of the Nation; yet methinks each mans private Intereſt, and the Laws of Self-preſervation, ought to perſwade us to pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for the Good of the King and Country: He that is not a Friend to the publick Peace of that Kingdom wherein he lives, can never be a good Subject; and he that is not a good Subject, can neither be a good Chriſtian, nor an honeſt Man: For the ſame God that bids us love the Brotherhood, commands us alſo to honour the King: 'tis natural for eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry man, to wiſh well to the place of his Nativity, or the place of his Reſidence; and how he can do that, without deſiring the publick Good of ſuch a place, I cannot under<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtand: every mans particular Advantage and Safety is a branch of the publick.</p>
            <p>There is no perſon ſo inconſiderable, but may contri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bute to the general Good of a Nation, either by his En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deavours or Prayers; nay, we commonly find, that Inſur<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rections and Civil Wars are often begun, but always car<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ried on by the Common people, (and therefore they may prevent ſuch Diſturbances) not but they mean as well, and oft times better, than thoſe that perſwade them to diſturb the Peace of a Kingdom; but they are perſons uſually of mean underſtandings, and are very often cajol'd and wheed<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led into Rebellion, by fine Words, and guilded Pretences.</p>
            <p>The beſt way for the ordinary ſort of men not to be caught in theſe ſnares, is, to believe and conſider that Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion is a moſt grievous Sin, 'tis as the ſin of Witchcraft; and you know the Law ſays, <hi>Thou ſhalt not ſuffer a Witch to live.</hi> And if Rebellion be ſuch a Sin, 'tis not the pre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tences of Defending Liberty and Property, of Deſtroying Popery &amp; Arbitrary Government, that can make it not a Sin: for however advantageous theſe may be to a Common<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>wealth, yet ſtill Rebellion is a damning Sin; and we muſt
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:97361:7"/> not do evil, that good may come thereof. Conſider in what horrid Confuſion we were not many years ſince, by our Diſtractions, Fears and Jealouſies, when there was no King in <hi>Iſrael,</hi> no Church, no Law, but every one was ſet<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ting up a Church and a Government for himſelf, and e<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>very one did what ſeemed good in his own eyes. Nay, many of thoſe perſons that were ſeduced into Rebellion, when they ſaw the Injuſtice and Hypocriſie of their Ringleaders, were aſham'd of their proceedings.</p>
            <p>Are not theſe Miſeries the greateſt that can befall a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion? And if they be, is not every particular man oblig'd by the Duty he owes his King, the Love he owes his Coun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>try and himſelf, to pray for <hi>the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem? He that can prevent a Fire in the heart of a City, and will not, becauſe he lives in the Suburbs, may, for his neglect, have his own Houſe burned to Aſhes, and he deſerves it; and he that will not, to the utmoſt of his power, either by his Endeavours, or Prayers, prevent a publick Diſturbance in the Kingdom where he lives, becauſe he is not a Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>man, does not deſerve to enjoy the benefit of publick Peace and Plenty. Though we are not all born to be Stateſ-men and Privy-Counſellors, yet every man in his ſtation ought to contribute what he can to the Peace of a Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tion: he that is not fit to be a Privy-Counſellor, may not withſtanding contribute to the publick Peace of a King<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, by being obedient to his Superiors; by ſpeaking well of the Government, if it be good; by ſubmitting, if it be otherwiſe; by ſtudying to be quiet, and minding his own buſineſs: He that is not qualified to ſit at the Helm, may by ſitting ſtill keep the Boat from toſſing. Let Stateſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>men, whoſe Buſineſs it is, concern themſelves with the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vernment; but let not every private perſon, though of ne<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ver ſo mean Quality and Underſtanding, trouble his head with the Management of a Kingdom. Muſt every private
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:97361:8"/> Paſſenger pretend to ſteer the Ship, that knows not at which end of her the Rudder is? Our Superiors may, and often do, order things for the publick Good, which to our apprehenſions may ſeem otherwiſe; muſt therefore thoſe not be done by our Governors, becauſe we cannot appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hend them? though the Sails of a Ship may make her lie on one ſide, yet without them ſhe can never reach the Ha<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven; if therefore a few timorous Paſſengers ſhould cry out, We are all loſt; would the Maſter of the Ship be ſo great a Fool, as to take down the Sails, and not only hinder his Voyage, but endanger his own and their Safeties, and let her be toſſed to and fro by the violence of the Waves, and all becauſe they that knew not what belong'd to a Ship adviſed him to it? There are Secrets in all Arts, which are not to be diſcovered to every perſon; and ſo there are <hi>Arcana Imperii,</hi> Secrets in Government, which are not to be diſcloſed, but to thoſe that ſit at the Helm. Some men are made to govern, others to obey, and we are bound by the Laws of God to be ſubject to our Superiors, not only for Wrath, but alſo for Conſcence ſake.</p>
            <p>If we look into Church Hiſtory, we ſhall find, that the primitive Chriſtians were ſo meek and ſubmiſſive to the Government, though they lived under Heathen Emperors, that they were the very beſt Subjects thoſe Emperors had. <hi>Tertullian</hi> in his Apology for the Chriſtians tells us, that the Cities, Corporations, Towns, Villages and Caſtles were filled with Chriſtians; yet would they not rebel, nor diſturb the Government, though they were perſecuted to death for no other end, but becauſe they were Chriſtians. Shall then ſome different Opinions in Religion make Chri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtian Subjects rebel againſt their Prince, and diſturb the publick Peace of the Kingdom: when the primitive Chriſti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ans thought themſelves bound to obey, and live peaceably
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:97361:8"/> under Heathen Governours <hi>Submit your ſelves to every Ordinance of Man for the Lords ſake,</hi> ſays St. <hi>Peter,</hi> who lived not only under a Heathen Emperor, but under <hi>Nero,</hi> the greateſt Perſecutor of them all. If every ſingle perſon would follow this Advice, and imploy his thoughts about his own Concerns, and not meddle with State affairs; we ſhould be much happier than we are; every man might live peaceably under his own Vine, and under his own Fig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tree. How uſual is it for men, upon a ſtory in a Gaz<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>zet, or a News Letter, to deſcant upon the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment, and cenſure, if not reproach the Higher Powers; when it may be the ſtory is falſe, or if true, they are not able to diſcern ſo far, as to know whether that which ſeems to them to be a Grievance, may not upon ſome other ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>compt then they apprehend, be a Benefit to the publick. Truſt the Modelling of the Government to your Superiors<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> whoſe Buſineſs it is to govern, and truſt the Events of the Government to God Almighty, who turns the Hearts of Kings as he pleaſes; and obſerve your own Duty to your Country, which is to obey: and though you are not al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ways in a condition of giving a helping hand to the Wel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fare of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> your King and Country; yet your Pray<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers for Peace will be always acceptable to God, who is the God of Peace. So much for the ſecond General in my Text.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The third thing to be obſerved, is the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment we have to be well affected to the Church and State, in theſe words; <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee. Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi> in this <hi>Pſalm</hi> is ſaid to be the place of Worſhip, thi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther the Tribes go up to teſtifie unto <hi>Iſrael,</hi> and to call upon the Name of the Lord. From which it is plain, that by <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> is meant the Church. <hi>They ſhall proſper that love thee; i. e.</hi> happy are they that live quietly and do not diſturb the Peace of the Church. And becauſe <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem</hi>
               <pb n="16" facs="tcp:97361:9"/> was the Seat of Judgment, it may alſo ſignifie the ſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pream Power of a Nation, and then the meaning of it will be, Happy are they that live peaceably under the Govern<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment of their Superiors both in Church and State, whilſt all they are miſerable, that bear Evil Will at <hi>Sion.</hi> That this is a ſufficient Encouragement to be well affected to the Government will appear, if you conſider theſe two things.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The great Happineſs of Peace.</item>
               <item>2. The Miſeries of a Rebellion, or a Civil War.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. For the firſt, as Health is to the Body, ſo Peace is to the Mind; it is the Foundation of all Enjoyments: how inſignificant are the beſt Meats to one whoſe Palate has no Taſte, and whoſe Body is diſturbed by a raging Feaver! and how inſignificant is even Plenty it ſelf in a Common-Wealth, that is ſick of Rebellion, which is the Feaver of a Kingdom, and is commonly occaſion'd by too high Feeding! the ſick mans Head is full of Whimſies, which make him rave, and ſpeak of things, which neither he, nor any elſe can underſtand; he ſeldom ſleeps, or if he does, he is preſently awaken'd with ſcaring Dreams; and his very Bedcloaths, which in time of Health were a Bleſſing, and preſerved his Body, are a Grievance to him. So 'tis in the State, the Body Politick, when diſaffected people, which are the jarring Hu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mours, diſturb its Peace. They perplex themſelves with ſtrange Fancies of imaginary evils, which no man elſe can underſtand, nor they themſelves: they throw off thoſe Laws that ſhould protect them, and run into greater Miſeries, than could have befallen them, had they really ſuffered thoſe evils they were afraid of. Happy is the man that bears a loyal Heart to his Prince, and is obedient to the Laws, that is orthodox and peaceable in the Church, and endeavours to preſerve Unity in the State; he is every mans Friend, and every man is a Friend to him; he ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nours the Magiſtrate and Laws, but is afraid of neither,
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:97361:9"/> becauſe he is innocent; he has the free uſe of his Reli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gion, and the enjoyment of his Eſtate; he eats his Meat with Pleaſure and Contentedneſs; the night is pleaſant to him; he does not dream of ill got Lands that are in his poſſeſſion; he is not ſcar'd with the Cries of Widows, or the Groans of Orphans; he is not haunted with the Guile of innocent Blood; nor is he frighten'd with the Ghoſt of a murder'd King. This is the condition of the peaceful man, and if a whole Kingdom were made up of men of this tem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>per; how happy ſhould we be? there would be no decay, no leading into captivity, and no complaining in our ſtreets. There could not be a greater Emblem of Heaven, than ſuch a Nation, where the only ſtrife would be, who ſhould be moſt charitable, and who ſhould be moſt loyal to their King, and ſerviceable to their Country. This is the firſt Reaſon to ſhew the Happineſs of thoſe that love the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love thee;</hi> for they ſhall have the Bleſſings of Peace.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, they ſhall be free from the miſeries of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, or a Civil War. The Miſeries of a Rebellion are twofold; Firſt, either ſuch as befall a Kingdom in general: or ſecondly, ſuch as befall every Rebel in particular.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Firſt the publick Calamities of a Rebellion are innu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>merable, I ſhall only inſtance in ſome of them that are moſt obvious. When people are diſaffected to the Government of Church or State, and thence take an occaſion to break out into Civil Wars; the Subject can neither enjoy the Benefit of the Laws, (which are our Protection in Peace) nor the Uſe of Religion, not the Profits of his Eſtate with out fear and danger: there is no Adminiſtration of Juſtice, there is no difference between Right and Wrong: Strength is the Lawgiver, and the longeſt Sword the meaſure of Juſtice the Corn-fields are deſtroyed; the ſtately Buildings are either void of Inhabitants, or are made a Garriſon and
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:97361:10"/> thoſe that are ſtrongeſt: the Houſes of God are profun'd, and demoliſh'd, and are made a Receptacle for Birds and Beaſts; and the whole Land lies deſolate: Graſs and Weeds grow in the Sreets of our great Cities, the Walls are bea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ten down, the Houſes burnt, and the Inhabitants fled or murdered: the Univerſities are emptied: the Liberal Arts &amp; Sciences muſt give place to the violence of the Sword; and ſo Learning is nipp'd in the very bud: Pride and Robbery, Ambition and Sacriledge, Oppreſſion and Murder, Covetouſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs and Profaneneſs, or elſe Hypocriſie, are the uſual at<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tendants of Rebellion. He that is in love with Famine, Plague and Deſolation, let him murmur and rebel; for they are the effects of a Civil War. If there were no other Puniſhment for reſiſting the ſupream Power, after this Life; yet the Calamities I have mention'd may be ſufficient to terrifie any one from it, that is not altogether void of Senſe and Honeſty. Rebellion is puniſhment enough for it ſelf. Theſe are the publick Miſeries of Rebellion.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Secondly, there are Miſeries that befall private per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſons in Rebellion. The ſeveral publick Calamities that I have now reckon'd, though they are not all, yet they are ſufficient to ſhew, that whilſt any Kingdom is in that con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dition, no particular perſon can be happy, But beſides all this, there is another reaſon to terrifie particular perſons from it, and that is the Execution of the Laws when the Rebellion is ended; for it cannot laſt always: what a Diſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grace, as well as Miſery, is it for one to be mark'd for a Rebel, to be proclaim'd a Traytor, to loſe an Eſtate, or an Imployment for Villany, to be hang'd for Treaſon, and to have his Head fix'd upon a pole, as a ſpectacle of Shame and Infamy! he is not only unhappy himſelf, but he intails Miſery and Poverty on his Family, and his Poſterity ſhall bluſh to hear him nam'd: but ſuppoſe Succeſs crown'd his Endeavours, and that Rebellion had got the upper hand;
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:97361:10"/> he may be great, but he cannot be happy: Fear and Guilt ſhall never let him enjoy himſelf, nor what he has unjuſtly gotten: and beſides the Hand of Providence, which is rea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dy to ſmite and pull him down; there is a natural deſire in men to deſtroy ſuch a Monſter, as being as dangerous as a wild beaſt: and if no body elſe will, God himſelf uſually makes ſuch perſons fall out among themſelves in dividing the Spoil, and ſo deſtroy one anothers deſigns; as it hap<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pen'd not long ſince in theſe Kingdoms: and to compleat the Rebels Miſeries, when his unhappy Life here is ended, he ſhall be thrown headlong into Hell, to keep company with the firſt Rebel <hi>Lucifer.</hi> And ſo I have diſpatch'd the third General, <hi>i. e.</hi> the Encouragement we have to pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem, they ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>In the laſt place, I will reduce what I have ſaid to practice. You ſee the neceſſity of the Duty of Prayer enjoyn'd in my Text, from our Wants and Neceſſities, and from the Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cy of God, who is ready to hear us. You ſee the thing we ought to pray for, <hi>i.e. the Peace of</hi> Jeruſalem, the good of Church and State, a publick Bleſſing; and the Encourage<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ment to this Duty from the third General, <hi>they ſhall proſper that love thee.</hi> You ſee the Happineſs of thoſe that live in peace and obedience to the Laws, and the Miſeries of Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bellion, both in this life, and that which is to come. Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſider the Folly as well as Miſery of thoſe that diſturb the Peace of a Kingdom, and the Diſgrace that attends ſuch reſiſting the lawful Magiſtrate. There is no pretence what<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſoever, whether of Liberty, Property, <hi>&amp;c.</hi> that can make Rebellion not to be a damning Sin. There is not any one Duty more plainly commanded throughout the whole Scri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pture, than Obedience to Magiſtrates. There is nothing contributes ſo much to the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> to the pub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lick good of a Nation, and the particular good of every per<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſon in it. There are many examples in the Old Teſtament
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:97361:11"/> of Gods Judgments againſt Rebels; and the end of our Sa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>viours coming into the world was to plant a Goſpel of Peace among men, and if the preaching of Peace was ever a Du<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty, it is now, by reaſon of the Diviſions among us. The great and general cauſe of Rebellion is Ambition, though Religion is often pretended: and therefore the beſt way to prevent a publick Diſturbance of the Peace, is, not to be ambitious of any thing that cannot be attain'd to, without an Alteration in the Government. Let us not ſpeak evil of the Ruler of the people, nor murmur at our Superiours, be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cauſe their Actions do not pleaſe our Humours; and when we find our ſelves oppreſſed, let us examine our own Lives, and try whether our own Wickedneſs is not the Cauſe of Gods puniſhing us with ſuch Rulers. <hi>Honour thy Father and Mother,</hi> which is the firſt Commandment with promiſe, is not only to be underſtood of our Natural Parents, but of the Magiſtrate, who is our, Civil Parent, and length of Days is the Promiſe annex'd to this Commandment. Saint <hi>Paul</hi> exhorts us, in his firſt Epiſtle to <hi>Tymothy,</hi> to make Supplications and Prayer for all men, and in the firſt place mentions Kings, and all that are in Authority, that we may lead a quiet and peaceable Life in all Godlineſs and Honeſty. There is more Weight than Honour in Government; and therefore we ought to be ſo much concern'd for the publick Good, as never to pray for our ſelves, but at the ſame time to pray for the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem,</hi> for this is good and ac<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ceptable in the ſight of God our Saviour: beware of aſper<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſing the Government, for there is a particular providence over Kings which will diſcover thy folly; if by murmuring and complaining of the Supream Power, thou art an Enemy to the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem. Curſe not the King, no not in thine heart, for a Bird of the Air ſhall carry the Voice, and that which hath Wings ſhall tell the matter.</hi> Is there not more wiſdom in buſying our ſelves with our own concerns,
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:97361:11"/> in ſubmitting to our Superiours and the Laws of the Land, that we may enjoy our Religion, our Eſtates, and our Liber<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ties (which are all the effects of publick Peace) than to ſpeak evil of Dignities, to promote a Diſturbance in <hi>Jeruſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lem,</hi> which does not only endanger our Happineſs, and Eſtates, but even our Lives, and the Welfare of our Poſte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rity?</p>
            <p>There is not any Church in the world, whoſe Principles are more repugnant to Rebellion, than the Church of <hi>Eng<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>land:</hi> If therefore you would ſhew your ſelves to be true Sons of that Church you pretend to, you muſt be loyal to the King, and ſubmiſſive to the Government; it is a Princi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ple not only honeſt, but generous, and agreeable to the meek Spirit of the primitive Chriſtians. They may pretend to Religion; but they who, under that colour, can reſiſt the ſupream Power, have no more Religion than <hi>Mahometans.</hi> To contrive the Death of a Prince, or the Subverſion of a Government, for the ſake of ſome Differences in Religion, is not only unchriſtian but inhumane. Let this be a gene<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ral Obſervation, That they who put on a preciſe Counte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nance, and under the colour of Religion ſpeak evil of Digni<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nities, murmur againſt the Government, and, when oppor<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tunity offers, endeavour to diſturb its Peace, notwithſtand<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing their pretences to Religion, and the Good of the Nati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on, cannot be honeſt men. Though the Wounds of our late Civil Wars are heal'd up, yet there are Scars enough remaining, to frighten any wiſe man from attempting to di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſturb the Peace of <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> a ſecond time. There are no Subjects under the Heavens, that may live more happily than we, if we, by our Diviſions and repinings, do not make our ſelves otherwiſe: have not we a gratious Prince, that is ſo far from oppreſſing his good Subjects, that he is merciful and even indulgent to the worſt? has any Kingdom in the world better Laws than we have, to ſecure the Prerogative
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:97361:12"/> of the Prince, and the Liberty of the People and have we not all the benefit of thoſe Laws to protect us? is there any one perſecuted with Fire and Faggot for Religion? is there any one that can complain that his Goods or Eſtate is wreſted from him by Oppreſſion or Tyranny? and if we did groan under any ſuch Calamities; yet the Laws of God will not allow a Proteſtant of the Church of <hi>England</hi> to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bel: though both the Papiſt and Presbyterian can make the Scripture ſpeak treaſon when they pleaſe. And if it be a damn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing Sin (as certainly it is) to reſiſt the Higher Powers, even when they perſecute and oppreſs us; it is much more hei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nous in the ſight of God, to reproach or rebel againſt ſo merciful a Soveraign as we enjoy.</p>
            <p>I pray God remove all our Fears, Jealouſies, and Diviſi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, and make us ſenſible of the Bleſſings of Peace, which we enjoy, and may the Kings Enemies be cover'd with ſhame, but on his Head may the Crown flouriſh.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
            <pb facs="tcp:97361:12"/>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
